yes might I hand up regulation 38 of the
value added tax regulations
1995 thank you very much and you H
punched
it lessons have I didn't tell my clock
to so I was at risk but my clock did so
that
broken um yes
well
um yes I also asked an authority which
isn't whole punched so sorry I might let
you down in a second um you'll see it's
adjustments in the course of business
you'll see at one the regulation applies
where there's an increase in
consideration or a decrease in
consideration of
supply and that occurs after the
prescribed accounting period in which
the original Supply took place so if if
the de if the increase incurred in that
prescribed accounting period you just
deal with it in that yeah at same
accounting period as the time of Supply
rules place of Supply but what you have
to do is at little two you have to make
um adjust your vat
accounts and over the page at
five you'll see you m the adjustment
when the increase or decrease in
consideration
occurs thank you very much
only defect with this is It's the
current version I think and I think I
should say Just In fairness I'm pretty
sure my recollection six used to apply a
different rule to an insolvent person so
for an insolvent person it used to be in
the period in which the suppliance
occurred but that's that's the general
rule then um the the I'm not sure
whether you want this now but just let
me test the aers and see um it's a case
of uh the case of in the court of appeal
of Mercy Global comp limited um well
that's why I was fairly up to date with
it I think we we we've had a word I
think our view is this that um at
present the right way to proceed is to
uh deal with the case as presented to us
by
you if um we think it important to
consider the possibility of dealing with
it on a basis that would have to
consider
whether
um difficult questions about which we
about whether we were bound which kadim
and therefore Mercy would be relevant we
will not do so without giving the
parties the opportunity to make
representations about
it so yes thank you that's well done
whoever found Mercy is the most recent
case in which in which um cadem has been
applied or actually not not applied um
uh there are others but that that gives
you the way into the case law so I don't
no need to hand it up thank you and on
especially as it do
punched uh and finally over lunch if you
go onto I hope you will allow me to lead
this evidence if you go on to government
do.uk and the check UK vat number
page um if you put in the uh V vrn that
registration number of a v group you get
the um name of the um uh representative
member if you put in the v registration
number and the suffix of an ordinary
member you get the name of the ordinary
member so you can find out that um it's
it's the public can find out whether or
not a um a person is a member of a that
group now I'm not going to submit
anything significant turns on that in in
the course of that exercise somebody
pointed out to me and I should be well
aware of this from my participation ly's
case if if nothing else um of course the
representative member uh of a that group
can
change so one person can cease to be a
representative member and another person
can be or become the representative
member and both were in the fat group
throughout that before and after which
is something else that we say mildly
supports the idea that you are um V
registered when
you're of a v group it be very odd if um
simply by switching uh representative um
members people fell out of that
registration but that probably um I
should just leave it there so unless
there was anything else no not from any
of us thank
you yes miss my if I could just start by
handing up um copies of section 19 of
that act which we talked
about at the same
time yes well this was um this was sent
to us this morning but thank you nice to
have
you see I've also handed up section
46 than
you thank
you um the version of section 46 you
have um runs for part of what was the
group period in our case which 20 2007
this goes to 200 three uh there is
another version for the period after
that but nothing has changed in
subsection
one this deals with um my Lord law
Justice new um point yesterday which was
picked up by my learning friend earlier
today about whether it's an apt
comparator uh to compare a that group to
a single legal entity such as a company
with different div Visions um section 46
sub1 and this section still exists in
the current version of the 94 act the
registration under this act of a body
corporate carrying on a business in
several divisions May if the body
corporate so requests and the
Commissioners see fit be in the names of
those divisions so it is possible it's a
short point it's
possible in the vat world to register
different divisions of the same company
as separate taxable
persons thus the as I said the analogy
is apt when they are not so separately
registered those divisions belong to a
single taxable person uh the single
legal entity and that is the equivalence
that a vat group seeks to
match and yes when you disband about
group you have different uh separate
legal entities but similarly you can
register divisions of a company
separately as taxable
PS um I wanted to start just by
clarifying there is a distinction
between the different parts of our
argument which may may simply be
misunderstanding on my part but seems to
have gotten a little confused in the
course of my Lear gr
response first part of the argument is
regulation 90 does not
apply because there is no Supply no
continuous supply of services which is
required to trigger application of
Regulation 90 that's the opening words
of that
regulation there is no such reg 9 does
not apply because because there is no
continuous supply of services I I
paraphrase slightly but um if we go to
regulation 90 perhaps it's behind tab
two in authorities
bundle page
they're subject to paragraph two below
where Services um skipping the square
brackets um where services are supplied
for a period for a consideration Etc um
and we say first part of the argument um
no services are supplied for a period
because the transactions that in fact
took place between silver Fleet and
credential when the two are that grouped
should be
disregarded so you don't get to
regulation
19 the second part the
alternative of my submissions is that if
I am wrong and regulation 90 does
apply so you do deem there to
be a series of separate and successive
supplies taking place each time an
invoice is rendered or a uh payment is
made in the postgroup
period um there is no tax liability that
doesn't create a tax liability of silver
Fleet
and that is because um silver Fleet
that's because regulation 90 cannot
change the fact that at the time the
transactions actually took place the
transactions giving rise to the supply
took place silver fleet was not a
taxable
person
and was not carrying on a
business that is the BJ rice
point and the Assumption in the first
part of section
43 but that operates on the assumption
that I am wrong on my first ground and
regulation 90 does
apply still no tax
charge
so when my learned friend said this
morning just taking an example um I
believe I'm not misquoting him he says
when I say he said silver Fleet not
being a taxable person is no
justification for not applying
regulation 90 um that is not our
argument we assume regulation 90 applies
we say that because silver Fleet is not
a taxable person at the time the
services were in fact provided um not
withstanding the application of
Regulation 90 there is no tax liability
attaching to Silver
Fleet my learner friend also said that
this case is about whether section 43
applies um we say there's no doubt
section 43 did apply it certainly
applied during the actual group
period
um no one I submit can can sensibly
argue against that there was in fact a
vat group and silver Fleet and
credential were in fact members of that
vat
group and during that period section 43
doubtlessly
applied what this appeal is about is how
you constr and apply section
43 during that
period and whether if I'm wrong on my
primary submission whether the
application of Regulation 90 changes
anything about how section 43 appli
during that period in other words about
how silver fleet was not a taxable
person we say and was not carrying on a
business during that period whether that
becomes Changed by the subsequent
application of reducation
it um so we're not saying um as my
learned friend described my argument um
we're not saying that the time of Supply
rules are to be applied differently in a
that group
context what we are saying is first if
there is no
Supply then there is no scope for
applying any time of Supply
rule point one point two only two points
um if there is a
supply um then you apply the time of
Supply rules but
if the supply was made by someone who
was not a taxable person and or not in
the course of furtherance of a business
carried on by that person then there is
no tax liability not withstanding any
time of Supply
rules
and those are both generally applicable
principles nothing special about a that
group
context those rules apply even when you
don't have which I say principles apply
even when there is no that
group
my learned friend said um and I must
admit it's my fault I didn't entirely
understand it but um he said it was
essential that the standard time of
Supply rules should apply when a group
is dealing with third parties
um and
I'm not entirely
certain correct me if I'm wrong about
the complexity he's talking about when a
vat group is dealing with a third party
the vat group is treated as a single
taxable
person when the third party makes a
supply to a member of the vat group it
is treated as making a supply to the
representative member that's section 43
sub one
subb and if a v consequence flows from
that Supply whether or not by applying
special time of Supply rules um that
consequence will flow there is nothing
particularly complex about the fact that
the supply is made to a back
group or to a member of
the
my learner friend um said that one
cannot determine when a supply took
place except by applying this he said
time of Supply rules I understand him to
mean the special time of Supply rules in
particular regulation 90 in our case uh
rather than what I've invited
uh your Lordships to do which is to look
at the facts of when the services were
in fact provided um looking at when a
supply when a transaction in fact took
place is actually a familiar concept um
in even in the context of the timing
rules if um if I could please invite
your lordship to turn to section six of
the vat act uh that's tab one of the
authorities
bundle page
seven
so if we could please look at um section
six sub subsection three it says subject
to subsections 4 to 14 below which are
the special rules and 14 then gives the
basis for enacting regulation 90 but
subject to those subsections a supply of
services shall be treated as taking
place at the time when the services are
performed and that's simply by looking
at the facts when were the services
performed so looking at the facts is not
a foreign concept uh in the B
scheme and indeed in many cases when you
have Services provided not on a
continuing basis for period iic payment
at the time of Supply is simply when the
services are performed sorry the time of
Supply I just didn't hear what you said
the time of Supply is simply when the
services are performed yes and that's a
factual
question um next point my learner friend
took you to article
64 of the principal V
directive and made a submission that it
does not rank any lower than article
63 um what he didn't do um I'm sure
inadvertently is take you to article 66
which is really the basis for enacting
regulation 90 um that's in Tab
four on page
35 um article 66 we've been here maybe
laboring the point by by way of
derogation from article 63 64 and 65
member states May provide that V is to
become chargeable and that takes you
back to article uh 62 sub2 becoming
chargeable means when the tax Authority
becomes entitled under law to claim the
tax um going back to 66 member states
May provide vus to become chargeable in
respect of certain actions for certain
categories of taxable persons at one of
the following times and then when the
invoice is issued payment is received
for a specific period from the date of
the chargeable event so what article 66
does not do as the basis for regulation
9 uh regulation 90 can't do is change
the time of the transaction which is
necessary to give rise to a chargeable
event and that's really Lord Nolan's
point in the in the observation he makes
in
Thor
then there was um a question uh raised
by my laws law Justice um Underhill and
law Justice Nui which is how does it
work with a single oneoff Supply that is
paid for
later um in my submission it works as
follows you um you start in section one
sub two of the vat act which is behind
tab one on page
three that tells you that on a supply of
goods or services is a liability of the
person making the supply and subject to
Provisions about accounting and payment
becomes due at the time of Supply so any
of that becomes to you at the time of
Supply then you go to section six which
is the time of Supply rules on page
seven and assuming we have a simple
supply of services um then we're in
subsection
three uh which we've just been to so
it's treated as taking place at the time
when the services are
performed that is when the tax is
due you determine the value of the
supply by reference to section 19
which I just handed
up so I won't read the whole section but
um you can see that if this is a
consideration in money that its value
will be such amount as with the addition
of that chargeable is equal to the
consider
if it's not consisting of money then you
take such amount of money as equivalent
to the consideration Etc so you
determine the value of the
supply and it's on that value of the
supply that that is
applied and if you need to have an
adjustment
afterwards
because prices go up and down
performances are better or worse than
expected um then you can do that that
through the operation of Regulation 38
which my learned friend has very
helpfully handed off and
explained just before I roast my
feet
sorry because that doesn't change the
time of Supply it just change no
regulation 38 doesn't change the time of
supply
but I think the point I was putting to
you was something like the facts of this
case maybe not exactly like the facts of
this case but where there are two
elements in the
consideration a fixed
element and an element which is wholly
uncertain depends
on um whatever it might be future
performance or overage
or uh
and I say future performance made the
case of investment something that no no
more services that you provide but
something that shows the services were
worth more than could be predicted at
the time of the original um original
Supply
um how would you apply 192 to
that so there are two
um there are really two at least two
possible commercial Arrangements that
might be captured the law ship just said
the first would fall or could fall
within regulation 90 because you have a
supply for a period for a consideration
whole part is determined or payable
periodically or if it is just no thought
I what you said 19 no I'm not I'm
thinking the whole point of my original
question was this is a one-off supply so
we're not in regulation 90
territory it's a one-off
supply the value of
which uh may be increased by subsequent
events uh the value of well the
consideration for which um uh so that's
the situation was putting to you
um you would take the the
consideration the value of the um the
value of the supply would be the
consideration in so far as one is best
able to determine it at the time of
Supply that would be charged to that and
if subsequently the consideration is
adjusted up or down one makes an
adjustment by the regulation 38
mechanism so the answer is regulation 38
so let's take a case where you're
paid uh
£100,000 but you may be
paid very simple a million
pounds uh three years later when certain
events either have or haven't
happened at the moment of the
supply clearly the value consideration
is at least the initial
£100,000 doeses some valuation have to
be made some guesstimate of what may
happen in three years time how the
market May perform or I if you allow me
a moment um
Mar I think that is right my Lord some
that's bizarre isn't it it's guess work
it's it's part of it's only
consideration
consideration assain notable up down
I mean have to I'm so sorry my
Lord um if you were my Lord if you were
to
receive say 100 um when the services are
performed um but there is a provision in
the Clause that says more maybe in in in
the contract that says additional
consideration well the consideration
rather the consideration will increase
subject to potential future events and
those events come to pass and the
consideration is increased so you are
paid an additional 100 um that is a
regulation 38 adjustment provided and
there is body of case law on this
provided that what the contract actually
provides for us an increase in the
original
consideration um then you are adjusting
that consideration bya regulation
38 yes I see so Ian the most dramatic is
I'm not sure overage would work because
that's that wouldn't be payable in the
first place but imagine a situation
where you're not talking about land and
and who's all dependent on some external
events if it were land you be talking
about the grant of Planning Commission
say or um
uh
I I see you would simply say the the
quite modest amount that was paid on day
one even if it's increased tenfold three
years later that's treated as an
adjustment to consideration three years
later and is chargeable at that at that
point you work out the consideration
that's given for the supply um and if
that consideration then increases or
indeed decreases yeah I think the
anything that was puzzling me and this
probably doesn't arise but is is whether
at the moment of the
supply um you have got to make an
estimate of the value of the overage
provision those behind you are are um
shaking their heads I I thought that
couldn't be the case and they don't
think it is well I've exhausted myself
on this point I don't know um new you
want to think about that it really the
answer is that it's it's it's although a
slightly dramatic example of it it's a
it's simply a regulation 38 situation
it's a regulation 38 adjustment of of
the
consideration
um my um learned friend then gave an
example um he said imagine if you had um
building Works followed by a period
where snagging um needed to be
resolved and uh he said you might take
the view and he said in the context of
this would be uh
it would create uncertainty and
unworkability if you simply look at the
facts of the situation he said you might
take the view that payment is due when
the work is completed uh before snagging
or halfway through snagging or when most
of the snagging is resolved or after
snagging is completed and that's
confusing
um in my submission the answer is one
has to look at the contract um you canw
the contract in a situation such as this
to
determine when the work is completed and
when payment for you it's no more
complicated than
that instruction exercise itself may not
be simple but it's one that can be
done um then I need to move on to Thor
materials
um there was a point that um my lord
lord Justice Nui raised about what Lord
Nolan said um at page
81 it's the part um the Commissioners
rely
on Lord Nolan says
um I accept Mr PR's further submission
that the time of Supply rules must be
applied to determine whether and if so
when a supply between members of the
same group took place
um and my law Justice new you pointed
out that that was Common Ground um just
to show you where that you find that you
can see the arguments set out at page
78 it sideline
over the page onto
79 I can't I'm afraid recall whether
we've read those paragraphs
already but there was no contention
between the parties in Thor
material that um the time of Supply rule
in that case should be
applied the argument was what was the
consequence of applying that rule
um still in Thorn but moving on to page
86 which is in Lord Hoffman's
judgment
um this is the bid between D and F in
the
margin and the question was whether
that's flatly contradictory to what Lord
Nolan and the majority said um earlier
in the report and my submission is that
it is is yes it is flatly contradictory
um I might read it quickly um take the
case of a company which agrees to sell
Goods receives the whole price in
advance but before the goods are
delivered or the property has passed
joins the group same group as the buyer
under the time of Supply rules the whole
Supply is deemed to have taken place
when the price was received and the
seller is liable to tax but the
completion of the transaction takes
place within the box if it cannot be
seen there was no Supply within the
definition of a supplying schedule to is
the seller entitled to repayment of the
tax Mr pling seemed cheerfully willing
to accept that he was but this two seems
an extraordinary anomaly Etc um so this
is an example an observation that Mr
pling accepts um if we turn back to page
80 in Lord Nolan's
judgment starting between C and D been
through this passage many times um the
coroller for present purposes which
again I understood Mr pling to accept so
it's in my submission fairly clear it's
the same scenario um was that if the
sequence of events in the present case
have been reversed and if the sale
agreement and advanced payment had taken
place before materials and home became
members of the same group but the
agreement had been completed after that
date any tax charged on the advanced
payment would fall to be refunded the
transfer of ownership in the goods and
thus their supply would duely have taken
place but this would have to be
disregarded under Section 29 and so for
the purposes of the charged tax the
chargeable event anticipated by the
charge of tax upon the advanced payment
would have failed to
materialize at two two points to make um
on the back of that
passage um the first is as Lord
Hoffman um describes example it's the
same example
um we're talking about a case where the
whole price was paid in advance and
there's nothing in Lord Nolan's
observation to suggest that what he says
there is restricted to um only part
payment rather than 100% of the payment
being made in
advance I point to this out because my
learned friend
um submitted that it makes a difference
that the time of Supply rule in Thor
material was
different because it was one Supply
deemed to be made to a certain extent on
the payment uh of
consideration if we turn back to page 78
please and there you can see the
relevant timing R set
out it's uh next to C in the margin it's
section was than section
five before the time applicable under
subsection two of section four above the
person making the supply issues the tax
invoice in respect of it or if before
the time applicable on paragraph A or B
of subsection two of that section he
receives the payment in respect of it
the supply shall to the extent covered
by the invoice or payment be treated as
taking place at the time the invoice is
issued or the payment is received so
where one has a 100%
prepayment then the extent covered you
the supply is treated to the extent
covered by the invoice of payment as
taking place at the time of invoice of
payment so 100% that is the whole Supply
would be treated as having taken place
on the earlier date of the
prepayment um second Point again in
reply to what my learned friend
submitted um he said that where Lord
Nolan talks about what is to be
disregarded um he is talking about
disregarding the supply this part of his
submission that there is a supply Supply
only part of which is considered to have
been prese supplied as it were but if
you look at what Lord Nolan actually
says between d and e he says the
transfer page I'm so sorry page 80 now
back in Lord Nolan's
example page a between d and e his
lordship says the transfer of ownership
in the goods and thus their supply would
usually have taken place but this would
have to be disregarded under Section 29
and this in my submission refers to the
transfer of ownership in the
goods it's the real world transaction
it's the thing that creates a
supply that is to be
disregarded
so that is Thor materials then I need to
deal briefly with
RSA my learned
friend I think I'm writing saying agreed
that what the three law Lords in RSA and
the House of Lords
said about what Lady Justice Arden had
said about BJ rice in the court of
appeal is now the pronouncement of the
ratio in BJ rice and that that is
binding if we just look at that um we
started don't think we need to go there
but we started in Lord
Hoffman's Judgment at paragraph
36 which
is
tab
11 page 30 page
156 only a short sentence um between d
and e in the margin on on this sorry I'm
just writing something down which page
page
156 behind tab
yes this is in Lord Hoffman's judgment
in
RSA simply he says on this point between
D and E in the margin on this point I
agree with the tribunal and Lady Justice
ardin and he's talking about the concept
um of the same goods or services being
supplied over and over again too hard to
grasp and that they should be treated as
successive supplies so he says on this
point I agree with the tribunal and Lady
Justice
Arden and if we turn back to what Lady
Justice Arden said which is in the
preceding tab tab
10 page 14
one it's uh her lady ship's paragraph
48 um You' read this whole paragraph I
don't think it's necessary to repeat the
first part of it but starting at just
above D in the margin um she says nor
does the case of BJ rice a decision of
this court on which the judge relied
require this distinction to be made in
that case very different considerations
arose because the issue was whether the
time of Supply rules could result in the
imposition of a liability to account for
that on a person who was not a taxable
person at the time he supplied and
raised an invoice for the services in
question and in so far as this case is
thought to EST establish any wider
restriction on the time of Supply rules
see per Lord Hoffman dissenting in Thor
materials so my submission her ladyship
is very clear as to what she considers
the ratio of BJ rice to be which is what
she describes as the issue in that case
and that's whether the time of Supply
rules could result in the imposition of
a liability to account for that on a
person who was not a taxable person at
the time he supplied and raised an
invoice for services in question
and I'll take you to the point of the
invoice in just a
moment but if it is right um and I'm not
making a big point of what my learned
friend uh said when he agreed um that
that this is now the pronouncement of
the ratio but um
clearly Lady Justice arent is not saying
that BJ R is wrong in establishing that
principle what she is saying is that Mr
Justice
Park in the high court was wrong to rely
on BJ
rice for the
principle
that you could make the same supply of
lease over and over
again
the point about the impulse in BJ rice
um I I've been through the Judgment
um I I believe I've picked out um all
the passages that um refer to the
invoice on the facts of that case not
invoice where appears in a quoted bit of
legislation um it really didn't form
part of the ratio of the court in that
case um there are not many passages and
it may just be worth pointing them out
to
Lordships the first is on page 63 so BJ
rice is behind tab
six
page 63 at the bottom of the page um
recounting the facts he also sent out an
invoice he also sent out an invoice for
£150 it was not and could not be a tax
invoice under the value added tax act
1983 Mr rise was not at the time
registered for that since his turn had
not reached the level where he was
required to register but Mr Rice's bill
for 150 was not paid and he had roted
the bad debt then there came a time when
he did register for that uh in
1986 there no finding and no evidence as
to how long before that date the work
was done and the invoice
issued we know only that it was before
that
date for the purpose of our task in
interpreting the 1983 act we do not need
to know precisely when those events OCC
so invoice recounted as part of the
facts then on page
65 at B in the margin the Commissioners
thus conclude that Supply in this case
is to be treated as occurring inut of
time when Mr riser's bill was paid in
March
1991 the alternative provided by
regulation 23 sub1 subb and that is to
treat the time of suppliers when a tax
invoice is rendered um was not
applicable because Mr rice never did
Issue a tax invoice and could not
lawfully have done so while he was not
registered for that so the only
relevance of the invoice again is that
it was not a tax invoice and so could
not trigger an earlier time of Supply or
deemed time of
supply
um and then page
71 just above little a in the margin tax
invoice must bear the meaning given to
it in paragraph 2 Sub one of schedule 7
which in turn refers to General
regulation makes it plain that a tax
invoice can only be raised by a taxable
person since there was no tax invoice in
respect of this transaction then the
date of payment governs the date of
supply
and and that's it in so far as I can
find and if I have missed um a reference
another reference to invoice I apologize
but the point I'm making I hope emerges
clearly enough of those PS that we've
just been through is that the whole
issue of the invoice in BJ rice did not
form part of the ratio in that case its
only relevance was that had it been a
tax invoice which it couldn't have been
because Mr rice wasn't a taxable person
but had it been a tax invoice it would
have triggered an earlier deemed time of
Supply um still in BJ rise but moving on
to a separate Point um my learned friend
makes the argument that Mr rise was
entirely outside the scope of that and
was not seeking to rely on a deeming
provision in section 43 and that makes
if not all the difference um a lot of
difference the commission commissioner
say clearly that they say that clearly
silver fleet was not outside the scope
of the vat regime that it was vat
registered in the sense that it was
registered as a member of the vat
group um a few points to make in in
reply um whether or not someone is a
taxable person is a v
concept Mr rice was not a taxable person
because he wasn't required to be
registered his threshold was not high
enough the turnover was not higher than
threshold I should
say silver fleet was not a taxable
person because it cannot be a taxable
person whil a member of the vat group
that's amply scientific a paragraph
19 and Maring tells us in so far as one
can construe domestic legislation to be
compatible with the that directive it
has to be so done so the domestic
legislation defining what a taxable
person is is in section three of the vat
act uh which I handed up
yesterday and that can be
construed compatibly um so that silver
Fleet is not a taxable person certainly
we say it wasn't registered as a taxable
person it wasn't registered in its own
name as a taxable
person nor was it required to be
registered
now what the commissioner say on this
point is that um silver fleet was part
of a taxable person um but whatever that
means being part of a taxable person
does not allow a tax liability to attach
to Silver
Fleet as a distinct
entity um if you look at section
four
authorities tab one page
four section four of the vat act vat
shall be charged on any supply of goods
or services made in the United Kingdom
where it is a taxable Supply made by a
taxable person in the Cal furtherance of
any business carried on by him um being
part of a taxable person whatever that
means whether or not that concept exists
which I say it doesn't um is not
sufficient um for the imposition to tax
to fall on Silver Fleet and indeed if
you look at section one which was on the
previous
page um subsection two that on the
supply of goods or services the
liability of the person making the
supply and subject to Provisions about
counting payment becomes due at the time
of the supply you have to have a person
making the
supply
um and that person has to be a taxable
person an entire taxable person not just
part of a taxable
person
there are also all sorts of potential
difficulties that could arise if one
were to recognize a member of a vat
group as a taxable person in its own
right contrary to what ampli scientifica
tells
us
one of which might be input tax recovery
um and that's um it's section 26 which
I'm I'm so sorry my lords I don't have
to hand up to you but um but we will
arrange for a copy to be um to be
emailed and also hard copies
delivered um you need to worry about
delivering a hard copy we have printers
just just email um but um it's only a
small part section 26 subsection one
says the amount of input tax for which a
taxable person is entitled to credit at
the end of any period shall be etc etc
but the entitlement to recover input tax
is an entitlement of a taxable
person now if silver Fleet while still a
member of the vat group is a taxable
person does that then
mean that silver Fleet is entitled to
recover input tax
on supplies made to it that it can say
um in its
entirety that it can say that um it was
attributed to its own making of taxable
supplies even though the group as a
whole may be making a large amount of
exempt supplies normally what happens in
that situation is input tax recovery by
the group is
restricted because it's partially exempt
maybe to a very large part
exempt
but if one is to start treating
individual group members as taxable
persons in their own
right that could generate all sorts of
confusion and potentially scope for
abuse in terms of input tax
recoveries there is also as my learned
friend um confirmed right um joint and
several liability of group members for
the groups about Li that obligations
notionally attaching to the
representative
member a single taxable person is not
jointly and sbly liable for the tax
liability of other taxable persons not
not
usually
so silver Fleet quite clearly cannot be
a taxable person that's amply
scientifical that's just
clear
and it is also wrong to try to CCH it as
somehow part of a taxable person because
it's part of a bat group that is
registered as a vat
group
um moving on to the next Point
um again I hope I haven't misunderstood
it um my learned friend said something
about section 43 sub one subb
potentially be notus given the
Assumption if the assumption is
construed the way we invite you to
construe and indeed apply
it
um I don't think we need to go back to
section 43 been there many times um what
the assumption does is it treats the
representative member as carrying on the
business of all the group
members what section 43 sub one subb
does is when there is a supply to or
from a third party outside the group it
treats that as a
supply to or by the representative
member they are dealing with different
Concepts one is who is carrying on the
business and the other is who is making
the supply to a non-group member and
both are needed to impose that liability
on representative member a
representative member needs to be
treated as carrying on the business of
all the group members and it needs to be
treated as actually making or receiving
supplies from third party in order for
the representative member to be subject
to the V
consequences um next Point uh my learned
friend talked about the purpose of
article 11 being restricted in this case
to administrative ease there's no
question of abuse in this case
um that may be right but what he didn't
um take into account uh is what The
Advocate General said in in the Ireland
case and
lorentia um which were approved by the
court of appeal in Lloyd's
banking I went through all that
yesterday so I won't repeat myself but
those provide important clarification
and guidance on the purpose and
objective of the vat grouping regime on
what it means to treat the group as a
single taxable
person
and and I invite your Lordships to
resisit those
passages then there is just the a final
Point um which is my learned friend
points out out that there would be
anomaly um
if the actual Supply in group Supply
were made by the representative member
um that he says would be taxable um even
on my alternative
submission
um that's not the
case because as ampli scien ampli
scientific is very
clear members of a v group cannot be
treated as taxable
persons now in the
UK the V grouping
regime article 11 has been
implemented through a mechanism that
treats one member of that group the
representative
member as the taxable person in terms of
in the sense that it is the
representative member that accounts for
that and pays the that and deals with
hmrc on those
aspects but that doesn't mean if I am
wrong on regulation 90 and one ends up
with a post group plasma that in fact
took place inside the
group that the representative member
becomes chargeable to
tax because it was a taxable
person under the UK
legislation
for the purpose of the charged tax it is
not it cannot be a taxable person as
regards in group
supplies
um my lords I I subject to I think um
section 46 the section 46 point I
probably should have raced it um during
my my submissions yesterday so if my
learned friend would like to respond on
that point um then of course he should
be allow to do that subject to that um
unless there are any questions from your
Lordships um those are my submissions
no thank you very
much well mantle um I hadn't myself
spotted that was any point um on which
you might be entitled to a rejoiner but
it suggested there might be um uh on the
second 46
Point yes no no unless you have a
question for me no there's nothing
on well um I was clearly absurdly
optimistic in my
observations yesterday about how long
this appeal to take but I would like to
say that none of the time spent has been
wasted we've been had the benefit of um
extremely uh uh sophisticated and
persuasive and well presented
submissions from both sides so thank you
both and those behind you who've no
doubt contributed to them uh quite a
part for that reason but anyway um we're
obviously going to need to take time to
consider our decision uh
judgments will be circulated in draft in
the usual way for the primary purpose of
uh enabling the parties to uh agree uh
consequentials or if they can't to
supply brief and submission so that we
can make a decision on consequentials in
time of hand down also for the purpose
obviously of drawing our attention to
any typographical or other minor factual
errors uh there are as you know and I
needn't repeat um uh narrow restrictions
on the extent to which the um draft
judgments can be circulated further um
uh and if you follow the guidance in the
Attorney General sorry conso general for
Wales you won't go wrong but if you
don't you may it can be serious um uh I
think that's all I need to say thank you
m Lord we have identified designated
Clarks Court
sorry sir you have yes I we had that
yesterday thank you that's very
efficient